WILLIAM ZHU

wzhu4@outlook.com | Bethesda, MD 20814 | 610-517-3106 | LinkedIn | GitHub Website

Professional Summary

Senior Data Scientist with 4 years of experience in hospitality, meal subscription, and survey program evaluation.

Tools: SQL, Python (pandas, statsmodel, sklearn), AWS (Sagemaker Model Pipeline, JumpStart, Redshift, S3), R, Git, HTML/CSS Machine Learning: Linear and Logistic Regressions, LLM fine-tuning, Random Forest, Boosting, KNN, PCA, Clustering Analytical Methods: Causal Inference, AB Testing, Network Analysis, Natural Language Processing, Time Series Forecasting

Education

The University of Chicago (Chicago, IL)

MA Computational Social Science (STEM), Quadrangle Scholar

September 2020 — June 2022

Courses in Python Programming, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Social Network Analysis, Algorithms, Discrete Math, Large Scale Computing

Quantitative Marketing Concentration at Chicago Booth School of Business

Courses in Competitive Strategy, Marketing Strategy, Consumer Behavior, Experimental Marketing, Applied Regression Analysis, Big Data, Data-Driven Marketing, Macroeconomics

Haverford College (Haverford, PA)

BA Sociology, Minor in Statistics, GRE: Verbal: 165/170, Quantitative: 167/170, Writing: 5/6

September 2015 - May 2019

Work Experience

Choice Hotels International (North Bethesda, MD)

Senior Data Scientist

March 2024 – Present

- Enable stay personalization by building and productionizing ML models to understand guest stay behaviors and preferences
- Enable marketing personalization by designing and automating processes to identify guest "passion points"

Data Scientist February 2022 – March 2024

- Built, productionized, and maintained ML models to predict customer lifetime value, likelihood for second stay, detect points
 redemption fraud & loyalty enrollment fraud, and monitor & correct bias for cobrand credit card models
- Delivered insights to the leadership team on Choice guest retention cohort analysis, Choice and Radisson loyalty member overlap, Cobrand Credit Card Holder profiles and usage behaviors, and drivers of guest survey LTR scores
- Nominated as Choice MVP award Finalist and completed Emerging Leadership Program

RealEats (Geneva, NY)

Data Analytics Consultant

June 2021 – December 2021

- Drove analytics insights that led to \$16 million Series A funding by automating customer retention cohort analysis reports for CEO, CFO, investors, and board of directors
- Improved 2-month customer lifetime value by 7% by identifying promotional codes associated with low churn rate
- Solidified brand positioning strategy for the CMO by identifying top customers persona using logistic regressions and decision trees; compiled customer database by merging sales records, Census, Zillow home value, and various third-party databases

Westat (Rockville, MD)

Research Assistant

July 2019 – June 2020

- Received the highest performance rating for all 8 evaluation projects by performing survey data analysis and report writings for clients including the U.S. Department of Education, Verizon, and National Science Foundation (R, Excel)
- Co-authored an <u>evaluation report</u> that led to \$260K in funding for Racial Equity Action Leadership Program by showing its effectiveness at guiding 40+ participants to craft company-wide racial equity plan through focus groups and surveys
- Co-authored a peer-reviewed journal article titled "Using state data sets and meta-analysis of low-powered studies to evaluate a school-based dropout prevention program for students with disabilities." in *Studies in Educational Evaluation*

Data Analytics Projects

Exploring Public Bike Share Trip Patterns [5-min presentation, blog post]

March 2021 - Dec 2021

- Discovered associations between Chicago's public bike stations' usage volume and crime rates, socio-economic status, and demography by merging and analyzing 300K public bike trip records, 210K Chicago crime records, 11K bus stops records, U.S. Census, and Zillow home value index (Python pandas, networkx, statsmodels) [github repository]
- Achieved a prediction accuracy of 70% (AUC=0.76) by using Random Forest to predict whether e-bike trips cross zip codes; implemented parallel computing on 2.1 Million bike trip data (AWS S3 and EMR, PySpark, Dask) [github repository]

Uncovering Links between Cultural Values and Company Directions [5-min presentation]

March 2021 – June 2021

• Showed that firms with an agile culture are more likely to receive M&A and investment offers by analyzing keyword frequency in 4 Million Glassdoor employee text reviews from 6K firms in the U.S. (Python pandas, statsmodel, nltk, spacy, fuzzywuzzy)